[SPEAKER_00]: If things... if you are seeing things in the right way, then something that you know is unskillful, say, lust, comes up, and there's a red flag goes up, or
[SPEAKER_00]: You can feel the tendency there, or the pressure there, but you don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the mind goes into that, just investigating, just naturally, like, okay, I got a red flag.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is unskillful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it unskillful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then the dominoes start falling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because in that cloud, you're not getting wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's agitated.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a way, it's just, you know, what is it based on?
[SPEAKER_00]: The body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That body over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in the situation, you know, with that view of that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: While it's, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like, eh... if lust comes out, there is automatically a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because you're not free from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because you're not free from it, you have to be doing all that you just described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not free, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: From the nature of lust, because you're still subject, or you're still liable to lust, means all those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's sort of going in the right direction, but it's still not there, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say going in the right direction, I mean, yeah, so you're trying to understand the nature of lust, so to prevent the future arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is much deeper than just one particular arising of one particular lust or anger or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that
[SPEAKER_01]: It is able to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, lust remains possible, and you are not free from the possibility of your mind being infected by lust, or by aversion, or by whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what you need to strive at.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the lust arises, if there is a pull, or if the anger arises, if there is an aversion, or whatever you want to call it, means that's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's already a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that that possibility of anger, and now the actual anger, affects you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever you do then, will be on account of that lust, will be on account of that anger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the most... that's already not good, fundamentally speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's still within that of... it's not ideal, since you cannot but not do anything,
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not free from the... the nature of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not free from the nature of lust, so you will end up... whatever you do will be because of the reason of lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the best... and that's what you can do, is aim that whatever you have no choice but to do, is aimed at undoing the nature of the lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restraint, reflection that undermines the nature of lust and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, that's a form of response, which means... and if you need to respond, it means you're affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, for a Patujan, or in the case of a Krishna view of, oh, that's not a snake, that's a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you have to go and find out it's a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's completely misdirected.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's directed outside, projected onto the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if... and that is a natural tendency.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if there is a lustful
[SPEAKER_01]: object causing, like, infecting your mind with lust, you try and find the fault in the object, or find the fault in the object that caused you the anger and stuff, and that's already misplaced.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be able to accept it, accept responsibility for it, means withstand that arising for as long as it wants to arise, which I wait it wants to arise, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to think carefully, and wisely, basically, make that whatever you do, won't be misdirected at the particular thing, or internally, or externally, or both, or neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be thinking about, like, feeling bad about yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I made a mistake, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't... or hating on the object, or hating on yourself, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to do,
[SPEAKER_01]: A type of reflection that will end at that possibility of lust, of aversion, of delusion, of the fact that you are still subject to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether the present arising just reminded you of that, that you're still subject to it, but when you start dealing with it, you wanna
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop your efforts, so to speak, that they transcend a particular concern about this lustful object or that hateful object, but start dealing with the nature of lust and nature of hate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's extra hard in the beginning because the mind is pulled by the object and the problem means the object, but actually it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why delusion is a habit that's been cultivated for so long.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, the assumption that what has arisen now, what bothers me, whether by causing lust or aversion, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you deal with it and you feel immediate satisfaction because you dealt with it, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You gave in or overcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's still misplaced.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the more you look at it like this, the more that becomes obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: That actually, yeah, I might be able to deal with this particular problem, with this particular arising, with that particular thing that I've just perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if I can't?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, more likely, and everybody experienced that, yeah, I can deal with it, and I dealt with it, and then what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Until the next one comes along.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the next one, and then the next one, and then the next one.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know, yeah, I know when I deal with something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't deal with it completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh, okay, I've only done so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that type of escape, and then it's not really an escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, in that... in that Hindu... Krishna example of, oh, you have fear arising on account of some... on account of a snake that you've just seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, they say, ah, but then you look closer and then turns out it's a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, your fear was not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's completely misdirected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, what if you can't look closer?
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if you look even closer and you find out it's a snake, that looks like a roe?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to have to do anything on account of thing, because that means, whether it's good or bad, you're affected by that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you need to respond to it, if you need to find out that that roe, that that snake is a roe, means you were affected by the nature of the arising of a thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you start thinking like that, whether you see a snake,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see a thing, fear arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the problem, that's what you deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not concerned to go and look closer to see if it's a rope, because, ah, yeah, good, then my fear is not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That particular fear turned out to be unfounded, but finding out that it's unfounded, it's a different experience from the original fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: So even, even if it was the actual rope that you thought it was a snake, it was a real experience as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was experience of something I think is a snake that turns out actually to be a rope, that it's frightening me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why... well, that's why that doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why psychology doesn't work either, in terms of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It always required this management response in regard to things that arise and bother you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... again, you just stop and think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I might be able to deal with this, but I might... like, now I am able to walk and find out that it's a road.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if I can't do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I'll remain affected by this fear that might be unfounded or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can say, oh, it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That fear is not real because that might be a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, in that case, the experience of unreal fear is still frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: So whether you label it real or unreal or both or neither, the fact that on the level of feelings there is suffering, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it requires a magical belief that unreal frees me from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no really connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only connection between the two is the ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that actually your suffering remains unaffected.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see a something, a snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever arises, there is always an implicit possibility of it being otherwise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way, oh, I saw a snake, Fireroes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't misplace the problem,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't project it out onto that thing that you just perceived, if you just take it as a reminder that you can still be frightened, means you're not free from the nature of fear, regardless of any particular manifestation of it, an object that manifests it, then, if you find out, one way or the other, that it's a rope, then that experience of the rope is the experience of the rope that I thought it was that snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a relief on the particular level,
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at it as a nature thing, it means, ah, next time, it might actually be a snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Next time, I might see a rope, that I think it's a rope and I'm not afraid.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then I come closer and I realize it's a snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how does then, like this, this interpretation of Krishna stack up, saying, ah, well, see, it was a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, your fear and your whole experience is an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing to be afraid of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what if it's the other way around?
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you think it's a rope, but then it's a snake, because there are snakes in the world, then what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you...
[SPEAKER_01]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, this illusion, you can still call it an illusion, but that doesn't reduce your fear in any way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can say, oh, crap, the experience of non-threatening things can be threatening if I find out closer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you reverse completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why you need a belief and blind belief.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby you only look selectively at the things that suit you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because in reality, actually, the latter belief is more close to the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereby you think that everything can be a snake.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because an arising of things, in general, upon which your existence depends and is defined by, will cease eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So rather than like, oh no, it's all illusion, I'm fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can undo it and say, well, even the pleasure that I'm experiencing here, or even the peace that I'm experiencing here, in that sense, you can say it's illusory, because it will come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you realize that's not the illusion they talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: They talk about illusion selectively, denying its existence, because that temporarily, momentarily frees you from fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if there is a mistake, you know, like if you're perceiving something that it's not like that, that experience of a mistake, experience of illusion, is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's irrelevant, in a sense, because whether it's real or illusory, the fact that it can make you feel, that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is the problem, not what you've just perceived or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just thinking like that becomes apparent that... Well, thinking like that will make the attitude of denial, saying, ah, the world, the experience, this is not real, this is not real, will make it basically hollow, impotent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's leaking here.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will make it impotent, because it works only if you don't look at the other side of the picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the denial that frees you from temporarily... well, seemingly frees you from... Ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah!
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm relieved now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was actually a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, if you reverse and then don't stop there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, deny your rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deny your snake by finding out it's a rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, deny that rope.
[SPEAKER_01]: Deny that piece as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why did you stop there?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're only going to deny the displeasure as a form of escape,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, why do you... like, you come in good faith, then not deny peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm relieved.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if it's a snake?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that just shows you that things are subject to change, even if they don't necessarily change.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, I cannot control things changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the peace I feel now, on account of this particular change, is out of my control too.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's frightening.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, at the same time, the suffering that I feel on account of these things right now, is also out of my control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's liberating.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, you want to abandon both.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to realize that, well, actually, it's irrelevant whether it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's real or not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is, it arises as such, and as such, my feelings depend upon it, and as such, I have no control over them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why arahant doesn't feel pleasure, nor displeasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not subject to, you know, to like delight and lustful excitement and that form of pleasure, nor he's subject to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because both are seen as dependent upon things that arise externally, and as such, something that is fundamentally beyond your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Seeing the danger in the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: The danger, the gratification and the escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification being just this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: The gratification being of things arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is a degree of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, gratification is confirmation and delight and rejoicing and
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to start seeing that pleasure, whether you're gratified or not, as impermanent, as lowly, unworthy, and a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like the simile from the suttas,
[SPEAKER_01]: A big cup of beautiful beverage, pleasing in every sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nice smell, nice tartness, nice consistency, nice everything, nice taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it looks beautiful, but it has poison in it, that you cannot detect, but you know that there is a poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's still not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the joy of drinking, of experiencing that taste, is also real.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't know that it has poison, you'll drink it and you'll enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you know that it has poison, well, you'll drink it and your mouth will still enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you won't enjoy it, because it will be over... overridden?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or overrode?
[SPEAKER_01]: Overrided.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be... Overroded.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it will be... it will be overwhelmed by the fear
[SPEAKER_01]: of the knowledge that actually you are drinking poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you won't drink it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how pleasing it is, fully discerning the danger, the poison in it, you will not give in to the gratification of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no... that's why, like, you you mustn't deny
[SPEAKER_01]: Things, even beautiful and enchanting things, because by denying them, the nature of gratification is being denied, and you're not understanding it, which means you're still trapped by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, it doesn't mean you should indulge.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, like, no... well, that means go and drink poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to refrain from drinking poison, but you have to recognize that the validity of its pleasure still stands on a certain level, on the level of taste, on the level of sight, on the level of smell, touch, ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that level, it remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can discern through that, and then the knowledge... Because that knowledge cannot be perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: Poison is undetectable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole idea of Krishna escape, of denial, maya, illusion, reality, just doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are certain things that can only be known, not perceived.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can go and see that the rope is a snake, and the snake is a rope, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can do a scientific experiment and find out that it has traces of poison.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if it's undetectable by any means?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can approach it through your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the only thing you have is a thought that there is a poison in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's so hard to develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it is developed, no amount of pleasure coming from the five senses can actually take you back there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the knowledge is developed on a more fundamental level that precedes the senses in that structural sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... they just... they're powerless then.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you know that there is a poison, if you calculate that thought enough... Obviously, if there were no poison in sensuality, no matter how much you think that there is a poison, it would not get established.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because in reality there is a poison in sensuality,
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking that there is a poison will eventually yield the result of you recognizing that poison in your knowledge, which is how the dhamma works.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is... if the things that the Buddha taught about were not actually already there in those things, you thinking those things will not be able to take root, which means arahanty would not be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because those things are there, thinking according to the way that those things are, will eventually make you recognize that those things are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes time, which is why the repetition is necessary for practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not you see it once, like you move the curtains and you see what's outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to keep doing it, and doing it, and doing it, and doing it, until that almost... that artificial view of looking for poison, which you don't see, you don't detect, nothing, gets so established.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it's established, then you will actually see the poison, see the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because that danger was truly there, your practice corresponded to it, even without your knowledge, and then it was confirmed, and now you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... well, that was the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's like transition from Bhutujan to Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't know in the beginning, but he's doing it and doing and looking at things correctly, according to the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is that faith as the first step necessary, that he had to take on something.
[SPEAKER_01]: He doesn't know if it's right,
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he kept doing it, doing it, doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it was right, because it was how things were, then that becomes apparent eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's confirmed from him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he doesn't need any more faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now he sees directly for himself that those things are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why you have the... sensuality is one of the... one of the types of... one of the assumptions, one of the upādānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just assume something based on not knowing, but then you have no reference to know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to accept and trust that there is a poison in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, whenever there is a pleasure, or pull, or enchantment, or delight, you keep, like, pasting the idea of poison over it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's artificial, because you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because it is actually there, and you have faith that it's actually there, it will... it will sort of take its roots, much like when you graft a plant.
[SPEAKER_01]: You bring a completely alien, different plant, different tree, different branch to this tree, and you graft it, and then it takes over, and then emerges and becomes a new tree.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you actually have to take the view externally, which is why an utterance of another is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, knowing how to apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why we refer to dhamma as the ancient path.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was already there, it just gets obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it weren't, no manu-crafting can take root, because it doesn't correspond to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it's necessary, eh... for a Buddha or somebody of that
[SPEAKER_01]: Standing, so to speak, two rounds in the world, because it's not enough to see it once.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might once think that there is a poison, that sensuality is unwanted, but unless you have faith, unless somebody told you that you have to keep seeing that over and over and over again, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means the true nature of poison and the danger of sensuality will not be discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not enough to do it once, which means you can't do the dhamma by accident, or by luck, or by sheer chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go, by sheer chance, I realize that there is a poison in centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's undetectable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's only not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there might be, because there might be a poison, even if you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the most you're going to get, a possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why sometimes a putujana can't free himself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a possibility of this beautiful, tasty beverage being poisonous, as a simile.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is always that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, unless you have a good reason to entertain that possibility and act according to it, you won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it just seems unreal, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seems... seems fake, seems artificial, seems imaginary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is, on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you keep doing it, it turns out there was a poison and now you're liberated from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have conclusions free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same principle like that when it comes to self-view, but you can't do that by yourself, because it's yourself doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to take on something completely externally by somebody who already done it, and then keep doing it, and then eventually,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will correspond to the nature of things, which is that nothing can be yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same principle of... like, it's undetectable, because your whole experience is about yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Someone says, well, it's not self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can be, oh, okay, there's no self, there's no self, there's no self, but then that no-no-self is experience of yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to discern the lack of self in the arisen things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't perceive it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the mind comes first, and all the senses meet in the mind, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why, again, the common contemporary interpretation of impermanence as a flux, and things changing, and the modern science has proven that nothing is permanent, because the atoms and... That's all based on perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I can say this chair is unreal, but if I'm personally attached to that chair, and even if I know it's unreal, you're breaking it, I'll suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not my attachment.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much you say it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've seen things externally, like... Because whether it's real or not real, or moving or not, as such, it is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that it has arisen means it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's just delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the type of the danger and the escape, the gratification and the escape, is something you cannot perceive through your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, saying that all of the objects are impermanent, ah, this is all changing constantly, that makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because as such, as changing constantly, it's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, you're not free from the nature of death arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca is basically the impermanence in terms of... Well, a thing is impermanent because it has arisen, not because you witnessed its cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature of arising, for that reason,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a subject to the nature of ceasing, even if it's still persisting right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's depending on something that I have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, if you see... Well, that's something that becomes apparent if you start looking at the manifestation of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say manifestation, I don't mean like seeing things through your senses or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean them manifesting as phenomena, which is sometimes through your senses, sometimes through your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even ambiguous, weird, delusional thoughts are real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can designate them, you can talk about them,
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot perceive them by your five senses, but you can perceive them by the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to acknowledge that, and then it becomes apparent that whatever has the nature of arising is out of your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you have no say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... well, actually, you have no access to the point of their arising, from where they arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just... they just... they're just there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just find them already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're just witnessing something appearing, when that thing appears, it appears as if it's there beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not necessarily time involving time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, this came yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously appears as something before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for that reason, you realize the roots, the foundations of that thing are inconceivable, inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what impermanence is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if that thing remains standing for the rest of your life, which is actually your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, like, have your body disappear, and get destroyed, and you still remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And things... things arise because... well, it's possible for them to arise because of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, see, but even that...
[SPEAKER_00]: There has to be consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't... you can't see that directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can explain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say, ah, because of the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you're conceiving that consciousness as the cause of the arising of the things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you're conceiving it as yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're enclosed within the five aggregates and they're manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the reason that they're manifested, they are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's enclosed within the five aggregates, as you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step outside of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't say consciousness is this, consciousness is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can't... you can't do that in a good faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can... you can have feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of... you cannot own them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can just... you can just... Well, yeah, but your description is such appropriate to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Saying consciousness is the reason for this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just appropriated it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone can't say it arises like this particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it is, by hand, arises within consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the self-conscious.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that would mean, like, consciousness is some sort of vessel in which things appear, which means you take the ownership of the vessel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It arises with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, within, your whole experience is within the five aggregates, enclosed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you have
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of my hand has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of having a hand arising in your experience is within already.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And saying that arises, oh, inside of the consciousness or inside of this means stepping, means putting it into something, which means you are that which is outside.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become the vessel in which things arise, therefore you become its owner.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever the aggregate is manifested,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's found there beforehand, simultaneously with its manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whether it's a perception of your hand, or your feeling, or just the knowledge of something, means it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have no say in that manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say, absolutely no say.
[SPEAKER_01]: They arise on their own accord.
[SPEAKER_01]: They persist on their own accord.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... within that, that's... that's why they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, witnessing something disappear, means taking an external view in regard to their disappearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, that disappearance will not pertain to anicca, which is the personal impermanence, the impermanence that frees you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you just witnessed it externally, which means that which was witnessing remained unaffected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you recognize, well, it's not... because cessation of things is something that's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, it's impermanent because it's manifested, not because it's ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, rising is manifested, cessation is manifested, persisting while changing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those things are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impermanence is in regard to all of them, not just bound with cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that nature of impermanence is superimposed to any of those particular manifestations of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on a different level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present, inseparable from, but on a different level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It pertains to the nature of things arising, the nature of arising, the nature of ceasing, the nature of persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, those three things have come.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have a nature, a nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: That nature is manifested, and as such, it's impermanent, for the reason that it's manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you would...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were able to be a creator, you would be able to take the possession of cessation, that thing, which means you can have it for as long as you want, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even conceive, you can't even access the point where things manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just find them as manifested, even if it's simultaneously right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as such, when they cease, that's also inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why the aggregates cannot be actually assumed in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: They cannot be held by upādāna in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't take them up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing that you can't take them up, that's how you take it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So again, arising is manifested, ceasing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resisting while changing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_01]: Manifestation is that which is impermanent, not those particular arising, ceasing, persisting or changing.